A Novel Hybrid Size-Shape Framework for Multi-Objective Optimization of Reinforced Concrete Frames
Jaemni So
1
,
Seungjae Lee
1
,
K
oichi Kusunoki
2
, Donwoo Lee
1*
School of Industrial Design &amp; Architectural Engineering, Korea University of Technology &amp; Education, 1600 Chungjeol-ro, Byeongcheon-myeon, Cheonan 31253, Chungcheongnam-do, Republic of Korea
Earthquake Research Institute, The University of Tokyo, 1-1-1 Yayoi, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113-0032, Japan
D
onwoo Lee (
lov1004ely@koreatech.ac.kr
)
Abstract
Employing NSGA-II as the multi-objective optimization engine, the framework simultaneously addresses two conflicting objectives: minimizing the combined normalized total cost-embodied carbon indicator, which includes both economic and environmental factors, and minimizing the average stress ratio, indicative of structural conservativeness
Ultimately, this framework effectively derives a set of Pareto-optimal solutions that clearly illustrate the inverse trade-off between the two objectives, providing designers with a quantitative decision-making tool to navigate the trade-offs between cost-carbon emissions and structural conservatism, enabling informed decision-making that aligns with specific project goals
.
Keywords:
Reinfor
ced
I
ntroduction
Reinforced Concrete (RC)
multi-objective optimization problem (MOOP)
(Esfandiary M et al., 2016; Ehrgott, 2012)
(Djedoui N et al., 2025; Faghirnejad S, 2023)
(Akadiri &amp; Fadiya, 2013)
(Paya-Zaforteza et al., 2009; Mergos P, 2024; Werner &amp; Burns, 2012)
.
This traditional approach has inherent limitations in identifying optimal solutions
Genetic Algorithms (GA)
gained recognition as powerful optimization tools
Sabzi
, 20
11
; Aslay S et al., 2024; Kaveh A et al., 2023; Dehnavipour H et al., 2019; Akin A &amp; Saka M, 2015; Heydari F et al., 2025
Nigdeli, 2014
)
.
(Govindaraj &amp; Ramasamy, 2005; Mergos P, 2021; Bekda힊 &amp; Nigdeli, 2013)
(Kaveh A et al., 2020)
Non-dominated Sorting Genetic Algorithm II (NSGA-II)
(Deb et al., 200
2
)
(Babaei &amp; Mollayi, 2016; Zavala et al., 2016; Nebro et al., 2022)
.
(Chutani &amp; Singh, 2018; Gharehbaghi &amp; Fadaee, 2012; Chaudhuri et al., 2021)
(Aga &amp; Adam, 2015; Jiu-lin et al., 2020)
(Kaveh A &amp; Rezazadeh Ardebili S, 2021; Kaveh A et al., 2023; Mergos P, 2022; Esfandiari M et al., 2018)
(Faghirnejad S, 2023; Kaveh A et al., 2023; Kaveh A &amp; Ardebili S, 2023; Juliani &amp; Gomes, 2021)
. This study directly confronts these limitations by proposing a novel framework designed for immediate practical application
.
The primary aim of this study is to introduce a paradigm shift in the optimization of reinforced concrete frames, moving from theoretical abstraction to practical implementation. We achieve this through a novel multi-objective framework that ensures both computational efficiency and the direct constructability of its solutions. To realize this, we pursue the following specific objectives:
A tailored discrete section database is developed to meet the design constraints of the given project, such as materials and section sizes
During this process, complex serviceability limit state checks, including crack control, are pre-processed
This approach separates calculation-intensive reviews from the main search loop, thereby enhancing optimization efficiency and ensuring the practicality of the final solution
.
Secondly, this study pioneers a new Hybrid Size-Shape Optimization paradigm. Moving beyond simple sizing optimiza
simply expand the search database.
Thirdly, the study verifies the framework's effectiveness. By surpassing the limitations of existing studies, the effectiveness of the proposed framework is validated through the adoption of buildings with diverse span lengths and irregular floor plans, which resemble actual building forms, as example problems.
as a comprehensive indicator of economic and environmental performance, and the 'minimization of average stress ratio' as an indicator of structural conservativeness. Utilizing the NSGA-II algorithm, the Pareto optimal front representing the trade-off between these two objectives is derived, illustrating the potential for designers to make informed decisions that balance economic, environmental, and structural safety considerations based on quantitative evidence.
DEAP (Distributed Evolutionary Algorithms in Python)
OpenSees (Open System for Earthquake Engineering Simulation)
(McKenna, 1997)
. Based on the outcomes of this process, constraints related to strength (stress ratio), serviceability (deflection, interstory drift ratio, top floor displacement), and constructability (upper-lower column hierarchy) are evaluated.
Theoretical Background
Multi-Objective Optimization
(Marler &amp; Arora, 2004)
. Consequently, the aim of multi-objective optimization is not to identify a singular 'optimal solution,' but rather to investigate a set of viable solutions that effectively balance the various objectives.
(Coello Coello, 2006)
:
Minimize:
(1)
Subject to:
(2)
(3)
(4)
(5)
(Zitzler &amp; Thiele, 1999)
.
Here are the key concepts for understanding ?쁏areto optimality??
Dominance:
Pareto Optimal Set (
.
(6)
Pareto Front (
):
Pareto optimal set, which exists in the objective function space.
(7)
The Pareto front visually clarifies the relationships between conflicting objectives, making it a very useful tool for decision-makers to select a final solution from among various optimal alternatives based on the project's requirements and their own preferences. In a posteriori preference-based approaches like this study, an approximation of the Pareto front is first obtained through optimization algorithms, and then the decision-maker selects the final solution based on these results.
NSGA-II Algorithm
(Deb et al., 2002)
. This algorithm addressed significant limitations of its predecessor, NSGA, including high computational complexity, absence of elitism, and the requirement for users to manually adjust parameters to preserve solution diversity. A proficient multi-objective evolutionary algorithm must concurrently achieve two potentially conflicting objectives: convergence, ensuring that the generated solutions closely approximate the true Pareto front, and diversity, ensuring that the solutions are widely and evenly distributed across the entire Pareto front. The design of NSGA-II is predicated on three principal mechanisms developed to address these dual challenges.
Fast Non-dominated Sorting
). These are the most superior solutions in the current population.
).
This process is repeated until all solutions are assigned to their respective fronts.
Algorithm 1
(Deb et al., 2002)
For each
For each
If
then
Else if
then
If
then
While
For
each
For
each
then
Crowding Distance and Comparison Operator for Diversity Preservation
NSGA-II uses a diversity preservation mechanism called Crowding Distance to maintain population diversity. The crowding distance represents how closely packed the solutions are around a particular solution within the same front, thereby indicating the uniqueness of that solution's location. This measure is used to compare solutions in the selection process.
) and the crowding distance (
:
(
8
)
.
Assign infinite crowding distances to the boundary solutions in the sorted front:
(9)
For the remaining solutions, calculate the crowding distance using the following formula:
(10)
Algorithm 2
: Crowding-Distance-Assignment(
(Deb et al., 2002)
)                              for all other points
Generational Change Through Elitism
Elitism is an excellent method for finding optimal solutions or solutions close to optimal in evolutionary algorithms. NSGA-II uses a straightforward yet powerful elitism strategy as follows:
.
(11)
operator (
Algorithm 3
(Deb et al., 2002)
Crowding-distance-assignment(
th nondominated front in the parent pop
Sort(
Structural Design Constraints and Penalty Function
(MacGregor, 1997)
following basic inequality.
(12)
refers to the required strength, which denotes the load effects (such as bending moment, shear force, etc.) generated in a member by the factored load. This factored load is obtained by multiplying various loads, such as dead load (
) and live load (
), by their respective load factors (
is the strength reduction factor, which reduces the nominal strength to account for material strength variability, construction errors, and uncertainties in cross-sectional dimensions. This factor is less than 1.0 and varies according to the ductility of the failure mode: a higher value is applied when ductile failure is anticipated, such as in tension-controlled sections, and a lower value is applied when brittle failure is possible, such as in compression-controlled sections, to enhance the safety of structures.
.
Ultimate Limit States (ULS) pertain to failure conditions that are directly associated with life safety, such as the structural collapse. The evaluation of ULS involves verifying that the flexural strength, shear strength, and axial force-moment interactions of all structural members surpass the required strengths under factored loads, in accordance with ACI 318 standards. Additionally, it necessitates compliance with the minimum and maximum reinforcement ratio requirements to promote ductile behavior.
(ASCE, 2016)
.
In this study, the principles of strength design methods serve as critical constraints that each candidate design evaluated by the optimization algorithm must satisfy. Specifically, the design strength (
) of all members must exceed the required strength (
), and serviceability limits, such as deflection, must also be adhered to.
1
.
Summary of Structural Design Limit States and Constraints
Category
Limit State
Objective
Constraint Formulation
Key Checks
Governing Code
Safety
ULS
Prevention of destruction such as collapse, overturning, and buckling of structures
Flexural strength, shear strength, axial force-moment correlation (P-M), maximum/minimum reinforcement ratio
ACI 318
Serviceability
SLS
Ensuring functionality and comfort by preventing excessive deformation, cracks, and vibrations
Deflection, inter-story displacement, top floor displacement, crack width control
ACI 318, ASCE 7
Proposed Optimization Framework
computationally demanding individual section review from the principal optimization loop, thereby enhancing both efficiency and practicality.
1
.
Overall Optimization Process
embodied carbon
) are pre-calculated through individual structural analyses (Step 3), and the results are stored in a database for utilization in the optimization phase (Step 4).
This algorithm initiates the process by forming the initial population through the combination of section IDs from the database and the rotation status of columns (Step 5). It then conducts repeated fitness evaluations (Steps 6??) for each candidate design. This iterative process continues until the predefined termination conditions (Step 9) are satisfied, ultimately yielding the Pareto optimal front.
Project-Specific Section Database Generation
This framework initially establishes a tailored discrete section database that adheres to the practical constraints delineated for each optimization problem. By conceptualizing the optimization problem as a discrete combinatorial issue within a realistic search space, it ensures that the ultimate solution can be directly implemented without necessitating additional post-processing. Given the computationally demanding nature of database creation, this phase was executed using MATLAB for its robust numerical computation capabilities, whereas the primary framework, which conducts optimization utilizing the generated database, was implemented in a Python environment leveraging the DEAP and OpenSees libraries.
parameters, including section dimensions, material strengths, and reinforcement details. The full scope of these parameters is detailed in Table 2. The number of potential unique sections, derived from the combinations of these parameters, is on the order of tens of thousands, making an exhaustive enumeration computationally prohibitive and unnecessary for a metaheuristic search. Therefore, a database of 1,000 sections each for beams and columns was strategically generated. This was achieved by applying random sampling to the defined parameters, thereby constructing a representative discretized search space that statistically approximates the distribution of the entire potential design space. This approach is based on assumption that a near-optimal solution can be constructed from combinations of these representative cross-sections, as it ensures the search space is sufficiently diverse to capture a wide spectrum of performance characteristics?봣rom highly economical to robustly conservative. The actual costs and embodied carbon amounts corresponding to the generated cross-section IDs are illustrated in Figure 2, and Table 3 summarizes the unit values used to calculate these properties.
The generated database is organized based on key performance indicators to enhance the algorithm's search efficiency
(
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="mclose"/></w:rPr><w:t>)
, while column cross-sections are sorted in ascending order based on the area of the axial force-moment interaction diagram (P-M Diagram) of the major axis. Consequently, within each database, a lower section ID signifies lower section performance and cost.
Beam Section Database Generation
Given that flexural and shear resistance are critical in beams, the design flexural strength (
) and design shear strength (
) are computed as primary performance indicators. The generated code initially calculates the balanced reinforcement ratio (
) in accordance with ACI 318 regulations. Based on this calculation, it randomly determines the tensile reinforcement ratio (
) and the compression reinforcement ratio (
) within a range that promotes ductile failure. Consequently, all beams included in the database are doubly reinforced with compression reinforcement. All cross-sections comply with the minimum and maximum reinforcement ratio, bar spacing, and cover thickness requirements, and they also fulfill serviceability requirements through crack width assessments.
Column Section Database Generation
Columns are designed to withstand axial force, biaxial bending, and shear simultaneously, with all strengths being calculated except for torsion. The generated code randomly determines the reinforcement quantity within the total reinforcement ratio
)
2
.
Parameters for Project-Specific Database Generation
Parameter
Beam
Column
Common
Concrete Strength (
)
21, 27 MPa
21, 27 MPa
Rebar Strength (
)
400, 500 MPa
400, 500 MPa
Maximum Aggregate Size
25 mm
25 mm
Geometry
Section Width (b)
200 ~ 600 mm (50mm inc.)
300 ~ 600 mm (50mm inc.)
Section Depth (h)
300 ~ 1500 mm (50mm inc.)
300 ~ 1200 mm (50mm inc.)
Reinforcement
Reinforcement Type
Doubly Reinforced
2-sided &amp; 4-sided patterns
Reinforcement Ratio (
)
Main Bar Diameter
D19, D22
D19, D22, D25
Stirrup / Tie Diameter
D10, D13
D10, D13
3
.
Fixed Values of Calculating Cross-section Properties
Concrete Cost
Steel Cost
Concrete Densityl
Steel Density
Embodied Carbon of Concrete
Embodied Carbon of Steel
2
.
Distribution of Cost and Carbon by Cross-section ID
Optimization Methodology
variables, a member grouping strategy for their efficient management, an objective function that delineates the optimization goal, and constraints to ensure a realistic design.
Grouping Strategy for Decision Variables
In practical construction settings, the process of grouping structurally analogous members?봱eferred to as member grouping?봟y assigning them identical cross-sections is crucial for enhancing construction efficiency and minimizing formwork production costs. Furthermore, this grouping reduces the total number of variables in optimization problems, thereby facilitating more efficient algorithmic solution searches
(
Boscardin et al., 2019
)
.
members is not considered a variable in the optimization process and is predetermined according to the method established by the user. Figure 3 illustrates the grouping strategy applied to the example problem in Section 4.1.
3
.
Decision Variables: Hybrid Sizing-Shape Optimization
In the optimization algorithm, each candidate design is represented by genetic information, referred to as chromosomes. The chromosome is structured as a vector of integers, which denote the unique identification numbers of the cross-sections assigned to each member group, as well as the rotation status of the column groups. The rotation status is encoded as binary integers, specifically 0 and 1. Figure 4 illustrates the chromosome of the four-story example building discussed in Section 4.1. This chromosome comprises a total of 16 genes, which include 6 column section IDs, 6 column rotation flags, and 4 beam section IDs.
4
.
Thus, size optimization, which determines the dimensions of structural members through section identifiers, and shape optimization, which strategically manages the lateral stiffness of the structural system via column rotation indicators, are executed concurrently.
Objective Functions
This study conducts a multi-objective optimization to concurrently minimize two objectives, thereby examining the trade-off between economic efficiency and structural conservatism.
combined normalized total cost-embodied carbon indicator
serves as a comprehensive indicator that evaluates both the total construction cost and the total embodied carbon. Given that these indicators are generally proportional to the material quantity and exhibit a strong linear correlation, they are amalgamated into a single cost indicator rather than being treated as independent objectives for optimization. At this juncture, due to the differing units and value ranges of the two indicators, each is normalized to the range [0, 1] prior to summation, to prevent the construction cost?봶hich typically possesses larger numerical values?봣rom overshadowing the embodied carbon indicator.
(13)
The second objective function, structural conservatism (
), is characterized by the mean of the maximum stress ratios across all structural components. A reduced average stress ratio signifies a more conservative structural design.
(14)
Constraints and Penalty Function
Table 4
.
4
.
Design Constraints
Category
Constraint Description
Formulation
Governing Code
Strength
DCR of any member
ACI 318
Serviceability
Inter-story Drift Ratio (Seismic Load)
ASCE 7
Top-story Displacement (Wind Load)
ASCE 7
Beam Deflection (Simplified Check)
ACI 318
Constructability
Column Hierarchy
Practical Requirement
Constraint-Dominance Principle
Constraint Violation (
)
(15)
(16)
(1
7
)
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> constraints (indexed by 
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> is the magnitude of this violation beyond the acceptable threshold of 1.0.
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> are set to unity (1.0). This is a deliberate choice to maintain objectivity and avoid introducing subjective bias in prioritizing constraints. However, this does not mean all violations are treated equally. A more 
implicit weighting mechanism
??/w:t></w:r><w:r w:rsidRPr="005D4DEF"><w:t xml:space="preserve">, are not arbitrary values but are strategically established based on structural engineering principles, code philosophies, and damage assessment research, as detailed in 
Table 5
preliminary validation studies confirmed that solutions exceeding these established bounds consistently required major design revisions
, t
hus verifying their appropriateness as effective and realistic optimization boundaries.
5
.
Engineering-Justified Normalization Bounds for Constraint Violations
Constraint (
)
Max. Allowable Ratio (
)
Engineering Justification
Code/Literature Reference
Strength
2.0
beyond 100% (a factor of 2.0) are considered indicative of a fundamental design flaw rather than a simple resizing issue, thus marking a hard boundary for optimization.
design philosophy
Inter-story Drift
2.5
This bound is informed by FEMA P-58 fragility functions, which indicate that drift ratios up to 2.5 times the code limit generally correspond to a repairable damage state, providing a rational upper limit for serviceability.
ASCE 7-16, FEMA P-58
Top-story Displacement
3.0
Overall building displacement has less direct impact on structural damage compared to inter-story effects. Higher tolerance reflects this lower criticality.
Chopra (2017), Dynamics of Structures
Beam Deflection
2.0
ACI 318 deflection limits are primarily governed by serviceability concerns (e.g., aesthetics, occupant comfort) rather than safety. A factor of 2.0 is permitted as a soft constraint boundary, acknowledging that these conservative limits can be slightly exceeded during optimization before triggering significant functional issues.
ACI 318-19, Section 7.3
Column Hierarchy
1.2
A tight tolerance of 1.2 is used to strictly enforce the strong-column weak-beam principle, which is critical for seismic safety. The 20% allowance accommodates the discrete nature of the section database without compromising this fundamental design philosophy.
ACI 318-19, Section 18.7.3
Algorithm 4
. This principle
) to be superior to an infeasible one (
Algorithm 4
: Constraint-Dominance-Compare(A, B)
If(
Else if(
Else if(
Else if(
Else return Pareto_Dominance_Compare(
)             both feasible or equal violation
NSGA-??Application
The optimization framework introduced in this study is executed by integrating DEAP, a Python-
based evolutionary computation library, with OpenSees, an open-source finite element analysis framework. DEAP serves as a robust tool that flexibly defines the fundamental components of genetic algorithms, including individuals, populations, genetic operators, and the evolutionary engine. In this research, DEAP is employed to generate individuals with the chromosome structure delineated in Section 3.3.2 and to implement the core selection mechanism of NSGA-II. The structural performance of each candidate design is assessed using the extensively validated OpenSees. Within the optimization loop, upon provision of the genetic information (section ID, rotation flag) for each individual, the framework automatically generates an OpenSees script to construct a 3D analysis model of the design. Following the execution of static analyses for all load combinations, the framework extracts analysis results, such as member forces and nodal displacements, to compute the objective function values as outlined in Section 3.3.3 and to verify constraint compliance as described in Section 3.3.4.
By integrating the execution of evolutionary operations using DEAP with the evaluation of structural performance through OpenSees, the entire workflow is completed to autonomously explore the search space of reinforced concrete frame structures with complex constraints, thereby identifying the optimal solution.
Numerical Example &amp; Result Analysis
Target Structure, Load Conditions, Section Constraints
The structure selected for evaluating the efficacy of this optimization framework is an eight-story, three-dimensional reinforced concrete moment-resisting frame, as depicted in Figure 5. The floor plan exhibits an irregular configuration with varying span lengths.
The structural analysis considers various load conditions, including dead load, live load, wind load, and seismic load, with load combinations applied in accordance with ACI 318 and ASCE 7 standards. The loads on the beams of each floor are arranged in a checkerboard pattern, ensuring that the loaded areas vary for each floor, thereby reflecting realistic structural design practices. Detailed depictions of the load-bearing areas for each floor are provided in Figure 6. Table 6 presents a summary of the load values utilized in this example. Additionally, the self-weight of all structural members is automatically accounted for during analysis, based on pre-calculated unit weights from the database. Lateral forces are distributed to each floor following an inverted triangular distribution derived from the base shear force and are subsequently evenly allocated to each node on the floor. The magnitude of the lateral load acting on each node is detailed in Table 7, with an illustration provided in Figure 7. The cross-sectional search space for optimization is confined to the beam and column database, which is generated according to the project constraints outlined in Table 2 of Section 3.2.
5
.
6
.
Checkerboard Load Pattern for Superimposed Gravity Loads per Floor
6
.
Load Conditions for the Numerical Example
Load Type
Parameter
Value
Note
Gravity Loads
Superimposed Dead Load (DL)
25 kN/m
Checkerboard pattern
Live Load (LL)
20 kN/m
Checkerboard pattern
Lateral Loads
Base Shear X (Seismic, Ex)
40 kN
Triangular distribution
Base Shear Y (Seismic, Ey)
40 kN
Triangular distribution
Base Shear X (Wind, Wx)
35 kN
Triangular distribution
Base Shear Y (Wind, Wy)
38 kN
Triangular distribution
7
.
Nodal Lateral Loads per Floor (kN)
Floor
Nodal Fx (Seismic)
Nodal Fy (Seismic)
Nodal Fx (Wind)
Nodal Fy (Wind)
1
0.267
0.267
0.233
0.253
2
0.533
0.533
0.467
0.507
3
0.8
0.8
0.7
0.76
1.067
1.067
0.966
1.013
7
.
Graphically represented nodal lateral loads per floor (kN)
Determination of Optimal Genetic Algorithm Parameters
comprehensive account of the decision-making process. For parameter determination, the target structure maintained the same shape and loading area as the example problem, with only the load value being altered. The selection of optimal parameters was predicated on the convergence performance of the first objective function among the two objective functions. Separate experiments were conducted on the crossover strategy, parent selection strategy, and population to ascertain the optimal combination.
Crossover Strategy Comparison
The crossover strategy plays a crucial role in determining how genetic information from the parent generation is transmitted to the offspring generation, with the optimal strategy potentially varying based on the specific characteristics of the problem at hand. In this study, we conducted comparative experiments on three representative crossover strategies: Uniform Crossover, One-Point Crossover, and Two-Point Crossover. Optimization for each strategy was carried out under fixed conditions: random seed = 42, population = 100, generation = 100. The generational convergence process for each strategy is depicted in Figure 8, which illustrates that the One-Point Crossover strategy most reliably identifies superior solutions.
This suggests that the One-Point Crossover method effectively preserves the genetic information of the optimal solution during the crossover process, as it results in less disruption to the genes compared to alternative strategies.
8
.
Parent Selection Strategy Determination
convergence process in relation to changes in tournament size, revealing that the most efficient search occurred when the tournament size was set to 7.
9
.
Population Size Determination
The population size is a critical parameter influencing the balance between exploration diversity and computational cost. Utilizing the optimal crossover and parent selection strategies established from prior experiments, optimization was conducted with varying population sizes. Figure 10 illustrates the detailed convergence process for each size. The optimal population size was determined to be 600, considering computational cost. This conclusion is supported by the fact that it not only achieved convergence to the lowest value, but also, beginning with a population of 600, the differences were negligible: 600 = 0.335, 700 = 0.343, 800 = 0.336, 900 = 0.347, 1,000 = 0.336.
10
.
Pareto Front Analysis
significantly after the 30th generation, achieving 100% before the 60th generation. This indicates that the proposed constraint-priority selection mechanism operated effectively, swiftly directing the search towards the valid design space.
(b) The graph illustrates, for both objective functions, the optimal solution within the solution set for each generation. The first objective function (
) demonstrates a rapid enhancement in performance within the initial generations, after which it reaches a plateau. This suggests that the 100 generations allowed adequate time for the solutions to converge. Conversely, for the second objective function (
), the optimal solution from the initial population persisted through to the 100th generation, indicating that no superior average stress ratio value was identified.
(c) The graph illustrates the final results of the optimization process, presenting a total of 23 optimal solutions. The X-axis denotes structural conservatism (
), while the Y-axis represents economic and eco-friendly indicators (
). Consequently, a Pareto optimal front was successfully derived, clearly demonstrating the inverse trade-off relationship between the two objectives. For instance, the most economical solution (
), located at the lower right of the graph, exhibits an average stress ratio of approximately 0.4. In contrast, the most conservative solution (
), situated at the upper left, significantly increases the cost score to above 0.8, thereby clearly illustrating the trade-off between the two objectives.
(d) The graphs illustrate the actual total construction costs and the embodied carbon associated with the optimal solutions. Furthermore, in all graphs, identical optimal solutions are represented using the same color scheme.
(
a)
(
b)
(
c)
(
d)
11
.
Optimization Process Analysis
asible Solutions per Generation; (b) Convergence of the Hall of Fame; (c) Pareto Front in the Objec
tive Space
; (d) Pareto Front in the Solution Space (Cost
2
)
Figure 12 illustrates the distribution of design variables and performance characteristics of the optimal solutions. (a) The graph clearly indicates that the most cost-effective solution is concentrated around relatively smaller cross-sectional IDs, whereas more conservative solutions tend to select larger cross-sectional IDs. (b) The graph offers a comprehensive view of each solution?셲 characteristics, facilitating immediate comparison: Solution #1 exhibits low values on the Cost/CO
2
Figure 13 presents the outcomes of the displacement constraint analysis. The inter-story drift ratio induced by seismic loads consistently demonstrated stable performance, maintaining approximately 20??0% of the permissible limit (0.015) across all scenarios. Additionally, the top story displacement resulting from wind loads adhered to the allowable limit (0.04m) in every instance. Notably, the constraints imposed by wind loads were observed to be nearer to the limit compared to those imposed by seismic loads, suggesting that wind load design conditions exerted a more significant influence in determining the section.
(
a)
(
b)
12
.
Pareto Solutions Performance Comparison
(
a)
(
b)
(
c)
(
d)
13
.
Displacement Checks for Pareto Solutions
Seismic Inter-story Drift (Y-dir); (c) Wind Lateral D
isplacement (X-dir); (d) Wind Lateral Displacement (Y-dir)
Analysis of Representative Optimal Solutions
To examine the distinct characteristics of the solutions identified on the Pareto front, three representative solutions were selected for detailed comparison: Sol #1 (the most economical solution), Sol #12 (the balanced solution), and Sol #23 (the most conservative solution). These solutions are located at both extremities and the midpoint of the front. The key performance indicators for each representative solution are summarized in Table 9. The genetic information constituting each representative solution is presented in Table 10. These genetic details indicate the final section ID assigned to the member groups defined in Section 3.3.2, as well as the rotation status of the columns.
8
.
Performance Summary of Representative Optimal Solutions
Solution ID
Total Cost (won)
)
Sol #1
0.3096
0.4112
27,068,446
83,211
Sol #12
0.3395
0.3794
28,772,553
88,274
Sol #23
0.8715
0.2179
59,107,481
178,647
9
.
Genetic Information of Representative Solutions
Sol #1 (Economical)
Sol #12 (Balanced)
Sol #23 (Conservative)
Gene
Section
Gene
Section
Gene
Section
284
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>350
284
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>350
947
600
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>950
560
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>300
527
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>400
988
600
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>1200
526
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>400
842
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>350
962
550
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>950
43
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>300
43
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>300
278
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>550
361
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>300
361
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>300
366
450
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>600
284
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>350
283
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>300
303
350
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>450
0
-
1
-
1
-
1
-
0
-
1
-
0
-
1
-
1
-
1
-
1
-
0
-
0
-
0
-
1
-
0
-
0
-
0
-
231
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>350
231
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>350
862
600
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>1150
176
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>300
239
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>350
461
400
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>850
222
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>300
222
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>300
383
400
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>750
171
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>350
171
300
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>350
897
500
??/w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:rFonts w:ascii="Times New Roman" w:hAnsi="Times New Roman" w:cs="Times New Roman"/><w:bCs/><w:sz w:val="22"/></w:rPr><w:t>1150
Figures 14 and 15 present a comprehensive analysis of the stress ratio and displacement for each representative solution. As illustrated in Figure 14, the economical Solution #1 demonstrates efficient material utilization, with the beam's stress ratio nearing 0.95. Conversely, the conservative Solution #23 maintains a substantial safety margin, as evidenced by the relatively low stress ratios of its members, ranging from approximately 0.2 to 0.6.
(
a)
(
b)
(
c)
14
.
Detailed Stress Ratio (DCR) Analysis per Solution
Detailed Stress Ratio (DCR) Analysis for Sol #1
Sol #12; (c) Detailed Stress Ratio (DCR) Analysis for Sol #23
(
a)
(
b)
(
c)
(
d)
15
.
Displacement Checks for Representative Solutions
Rep. Solutions; (b)
Seismic Inter-story Drift (Y-dir) for Rep. Solutions; (c) Wind La
teral Displacement (X-dir) for Rep. Solutions; (d) Wind Later
al Displacement (Y-dir) for Rep. Solutions
D
iscussion
with a 25% lower average stress ratio (from ~0.4 to ~0.3, enhancing long-term durability and user comfort), it would require an additional investment of approximately ??5 million, leading to the design represented by Sol #18." This quantitative dialogue transforms abstract safety goals into concrete budget discussions, empowering stakeholders to make informed choices aligned with project-specific priorities.
Framework Performance Validation
framework, two key validation experiments were conducted. The first experiment focused on evaluating the consistency and reproducibility of the algorithm, while the second aimed to quantitatively analyze the computational efficiency of incorporating
Validation of Algorithm Consistency and Reproducibility
Considering the stochastic nature of metaheuristic algorithms, it is essential to verify that they produce consistent performance across independent executions. To this end, three independent optimization trials were performed using the identical example problem and optimization parameters.
Figure 16(a) illustrates the generational convergence process for objective function 1 (the cost-carbon indicator) for all three trials. As the graph shows, while there are slight path variations in the initial exploration phase due to stochastic differences, all three trials stably converge to a narrow range between 0.31 and 0.32 after approximately 70 generations.
) from the Pareto front of each trial. The optimal solution from Trial 1 recorded a cost of ??7,068,446 and 83,211
, while Trial 2 yielded ??7,586,835 and 83,108
, and Trial 3 resulted in ??7,652,633 and 85,267
. These values lie within a slight deviation of approximately 2.1% at maximum, indicating a very high level of consistency between the independent runs.
These results validate the robustness of the implemented NSGA-II algorithm. They clearly demonstrate that despite the inherent randomness of evolutionary algorithms, the proposed framework can consistently converge to high-quality, near-optimal solutions within an acceptable margin of error.
(
a)
(
b)
F
igure 16.
Comparison of Three Independent Optimization Trials
??/w:t></w:r><w:r w:rsidR="004A7A3A"><w:t xml:space="preserve"> Actual
ues Comparison
Validation of Hybrid Size-Shape Optimization Efficiency
variable, a comparative analysis was conducted between the following two scenarios:
Scenario A (Hybrid Approach): Utilizes the base section database (1,000 sections) and treats column rotation as a separate binary gene (total of 16 genes).
Scenario B (Extended Database Approach): Utilizes an extended database comprising the
In this comparative experiment, a unidirectional lateral load (X-direction only) was applied to maximize the effect of column rotation. This loading condition amplifies the directional stiffness requirements of the structural system, providing an optimal environment to observe the benefits of intell
igent column orientation management.
to identify promising design regions, the hybrid approach (Scenario A) overtakes it in performance after approximately 25 generations and continues to widen the gap.
This transition stems from the core efficiency of the hybrid approach. Scenario A can quickly determine the optimal column orientations, effectively solving the 'shape optimization' problem first. It then focuses its search on 'size optimization' within a reduced search space. This dynamically reduces the dimensionality of the problem, maximizing search efficiency. Ultimately, the hybrid approach achieved an objective function value approaching 0.30, while the extended database approach plateaued around 0.33, representing a performance improvement of over 9%.
Particularly noteworthy is the convergence stability in the later generations. Whereas Scenario B exhibits a relatively unstable convergence pattern as it continues to
F
igure 17.
Conclusion and Future Work
indicator?봞nd derived a Pareto optimal front that provides designers with a quantitative basis for informed decision-making.
Notably, this study validated the convergence stability and reproducibility of the proposed framework through independent trials. Furthermore, a comparative analysis against a traditional extended-database approach quantitatively verified the superiority of the hybrid method. The strategy of decoupling column rotation as an independent variable was shown to dynamically reduce the search space, leading to a performance improvement of over 9% and more stable convergence.
Nevertheless, this study has several limitations. First, the cross-sectional data was generated with a uniform stirrup spacing, which may not be optimal for shear resistance in all member regions. Second, costs related to rebar splicing, anchorage, and formwork were not included in the objective function. Finally, the member grouping strategy was predetermined
Future research will be directed at addressing these limitations. First, the database generation process will be refined to allow for variable stirrup spacing along member lengths. The economic model will also be expanded to include costs associated with splicing, anchorage, and formwork to provide a more holistic cost assessment. Finally, an advanced optimization module will be developed to allow the algorithm to intelligently determine optimal member groupings, further expanding the search for more innovative and efficient structural systems.
Disclosure statement
Data availability
Funding
References
Aga, A. A., &amp; Adam, F. M. (2015). Design optimization of reinforced concrete frames.
Open Journal of Civil Engineering
05
(01), 74??3. https://doi.org/10.4236/OJCE.2015.51008
Construction Innovation, 13
(4), 352-373.
Akin, A., &amp; Saka, M. P. (2015). Harmony search algorithm based optimum detailed design of reinforced concrete plane frames subject to ACI 318-05 provisions.혻
Computers &amp; Structures
,혻
147
, 79-95.
Aslay, S. E., Dede, T., &amp; Kaveh, A. (2024). Integrated design optimization process for building projects.혻
Periodica Polytechnica Civil Engineering
,혻
68
(4), 1175-1183.
https://doi.org/10.3311/PPCI.37113
Babaei, M., &amp; Mollayi, M. (2016). Multi-objective optimization of reinforced concrete frames using NSGA-II algorithm.혻
Engineering Structures and Technologies
,혻
8
(4), 157-164.
BAI, J. L., CHEN, H. M., SUN, B. H., &amp; JIN, S. S. (2020). Seismic uniform damage-targeted design of RC frame structures.혻
Engineering Mechanics
,혻
37
(8), 179-188.
Bekda힊, G. E. B. R. A. 캅. L., &amp; Nigdeli, S. M. (2014, July). Optimization of RC frame structures subjected to static loading. In혻
11th World Congress on Computational Mechanics
혻(pp. 20-25).
Boscardin, J. T., Yepes, V., &amp; Kripka, M. (2019). Optimization of reinforced concrete building frames with automated grouping of columns.혻
Automation in Construction
,혻
104
, 331-340.
Chaudhuri, P., Barman, S., Maity, D., &amp; Maiti, D. K. (2021). Cost effective design of RC building frame employing unified particle swarm optimization.
Chopra,혻A.혻K.혻(2017).혻Dynamics of Structures: Theory and Applications to Earthquake Engineering.혻Pearson.
Chutani, S., &amp; Singh, J. (2018). Use of modified hybrid PSOGSA for optimum design of RC frame.혻
Journal of the Chinese Institute of Engineers
,혻
41
(4), 342-352.
Coello, C. C. (2006). Evolutionary multi-objective optimization: a historical view of the field.혻
IEEE computational intelligence magazine
,혻
1
(1), 28-36.
Deb, K., Pratap, A., Agarwal, S., &amp; Meyarivan, T. A. M. T. (2002). A fast and elitist multiobjective genetic algorithm: NSGA-II.혻
IEEE transactions on evolutionary computation
,혻
6
(2), 182-197.
Dehnavipour, H., Mehrabani, M., Fakhriyat, A., &amp; Jakubczyk-Ga흢czy흦ska, A. (2019). Optimization-based design of 3D reinforced concrete structures.혻
Journal of soft computing in civil engineering
,혻
3
(3), 95-106.
Djedoui, N., Djafar-Henni, N., Bekda힊, G., Nigdeli, S. M., &amp; Chebili, R. (2025). Design Optimization of Seismic Reinforced 3D Concrete Frame Structures: A Computational Framework for Cost Efficiency Using the Hybrid PSOGWO Algorithm.혻
Iranian Journal of Science and Technology, Transactions of Civil Engineering
, 1-22.
Ehrgott, M. (2012). Vilfredo Pareto and multi-objective optimization.혻
Doc. math
,혻
8
, 447-453.
of 3D reinforced concrete frames using DMPSO algorithm.혻
Advances in Engineering Software
,혻
115
, 149-160.
Esfandiary, M. J., Sheikholarefin, S., &amp; Bondarabadi, H. R. (2016). A combination of particle swarm optimization and multi-criterion decision-making for optimum design of reinforced concrete frames.혻
International journal of optimization in civil engineering
,혻
6
(2), 245-268.
Faghirnejad, S. (2023). Performance-Based Optimization of 2D Reinforced Concrete Moment Frames through Pushover Analysis and ABC Optimization Algorithm.혻
arXiv preprint arXiv:2312.09450
.
Gharehbaghi, S. (2012). Design optimization of RC frames under earthquake loads.혻
Iran University of Science &amp; Technology
.
Govindaraj, V., &amp; Ramasamy, J. V. (2005). Optimum detailed design of reinforced concrete continuous beams using genetic algorithms.혻
Computers &amp; structures
,혻
84
(1-2), 34-48.
Heydari, F., Andalib, M., Epackachi, S., &amp; Rafiee-Dehkharghani, R. (2025). Optimized design of RC moment frames with machine learning methods.혻
Journal of Building Engineering
,혻
104
, 112222.
Kaveh, A., &amp; Ardebili, S. R. (2023). Optimal design of mixed structures under time-history loading using metaheuristic algorithm.혻
Periodica Polytechnica Civil Engineering
,혻
67
(1), 57-64.
Kaveh, A., Izadifard, R. A., &amp; Mottaghi, L. (2020). Cost optimization of RC frames using automated member grouping.혻
International Journal of Optimization in Civil Engineering
,혻
10
(1), 91-100.
Kaveh, A., Izadifard, R. A., &amp; Mottaghi, L. (2020). Optimal design of planar RC frames considering CO2 emissions using ECBO, EVPS and PSO metaheuristic algorithms.혻
Journal of Building Engineering
,혻
28
, 101014.
algorithm for optimal design of reinforced concrete frames under time-history loading. In혻
Structures
혻(Vol. 34, pp. 758-770). Elsevier.
Kaveh, A., &amp; Ardebili, S. R. (2023, February). Optimum design of 3D reinforced concrete frames using IPGO algorithm. In혻
Structures
혻(Vol. 48, pp. 1848-1855). Elsevier.
Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA). (2012). Seismic Performance Assessment of Buildings Volume 1-Methodology.혻
Rep. No. FEMA P-58-1
.
Marler, R. T., &amp; Arora, J. S. (2004). Survey of multi-objective optimization methods for engineering.혻
Structural and multidisciplinary optimization
,혻
26
(6), 369-395.
Mazzoni, S., McKenna, F., Scott, M. H., &amp; Fenves, G. L. (2006). Open system for earthquake engineering simulation (opensees) opensees command language manual.혻
Pacific Earthquake Engineering Research Center
, 1-465.
Mergos, P. E. (2021). Optimum design of 3D reinforced concrete building frames with the flower pollination algorithm.혻
Journal of Building Engineering
,혻
44
, 102935.
Mergos, P. E. (2022). Surrogate-based optimum design of 3D reinforced concrete building frames to Eurocodes.혻
Developments in the Built Environment
,혻
11
, 100079.
Mergos, P. E. (2024). Structural design of reinforced concrete frames for minimum amount of concrete or embodied carbon.혻
Energy and Buildings
,혻
318
, 114505.
Nebro, A. J., Galeano-Brajones, J., Luna, F., &amp; Coello Coello, C. A. (2022). Is NSGA-II ready for large-scale multi-objective optimization?.혻
Mathematical and Computational Applications
,혻
27
(6), 103.
Paya-Zaforteza, I., Yepes, V., Hospitaler, A., &amp; Gonzalez-Vidosa, F. (2009). CO2-optimization of reinforced concrete frames by simulated annealing.혻
Engineering Structures
,혻
31
(7), 1501-1508.
Werner, W., &amp; Burns, J. G. (2012). Quantification and optimization of structural embodied energy and carbon. In혻
Structures Congress 2012
혻(pp. 929-940).
Zavala, G., Nebro, A. J., Luna, F., &amp; Coello Coello, C. A. (2016). Structural design using multi-objective metaheuristics. Comparative study and application to a real-world problem.혻
Structural and Multidisciplinary Optimization
,혻
53
(3), 545-566.
Zitzler, E., &amp; Thiele, L. (2002). Multiobjective evolutionary algorithms: a comparative case study and the strength Pareto approach.혻
IEEE transactions on Evolutionary Computation
,혻
3
(4), 257-271.
Kaveh, A., &amp; Sabzi, O. (2011). A comparative study of two meta-heuristic algorithms for optimum design of reinforced concrete frames.
McKenna, F. T. (1997).혻
Object-oriented finite element programming: frameworks for analysis, algorithms and parallel computing
. University of California, Berkeley.
